I'm going to discuss mutable and immutable data types and functions.
本视频将讲解可变和不可变数据类型及函数
Recall, you discussed mutable and immutable data types
回想一下 我们曾经探讨过可变与不可变数据类型
in the lesson Data Types and Operators,
当时上的课程是
Lists and Membership Operators.
数据类型、运算符、列表与成员运算符
To review, mutable data types can be changed after
重温一下 可变数据类型
they're created and immutable data types can't.
在创建后可以更改 不可变数据类型则不能
Immutable data types are boolean values, integers, floats, tuples,
不可变数据类型有布尔值、整数、浮点数、元组和字符串
and strings whereas mutable data types are lists, dictionaries, and sets.
而可变数据类型有列表、字典和集合
As you learned in the lesson, Functions Variable Scope,
正如课程 “函数-变量范围” 所讲
immutable data types are passed into functions as a copy of the original object.
不可变数据类型是以原对象副本的形式输入函数的
This means that the changes that happen to the copy don't affect that original object.
也就是说 副本发生的变化不会影响原对象
Whereas with mutable data types,
而可变数据类型
they're passed into functions as a pointer to the original object.
则是以原对象指针的形式输入函数的
This means that changes that happened to that pointer within the function,
也就意味着无论指针在函数里有何变化
change that original object.
原对象都会随之改变
You can review the lesson,
你可以复习
Functions Variable Scope, to review the scope of immutable data types.
“函数-变量范围” 一课 重温不可变数据类型的范围
With this video, we'll be learning about the scope
本视频将讲授可变数据类型的范围
of mutable data types with the next three examples.
并借助三个例子进行阐述
Although our examples show lists,
虽然我们以列表为例
the same will be true for any mutable data type,
但其原理适用于其它任意可变数据类型
like a dictionary or a set.
比如字典或集合
With our first example,
第一个例子
we'll see how a list scope is extended into a function,
列表范围会延伸到函数内部
when that list is created outside the function,
此时列表是在函数外部创建的
and then passed into that function as an argument.
并以参数的形式输入到函数内部
With our second example,
第二个例子
we'll see that a list scope is limited to a function if
列表范围局限于函数之内
that list is created within the function and not returned from that function.
此时列表由函数创建 但不会经函数返回而出
With our third example,
第三个例子
we'll see a list scope can be extended beyond a function
列表范围可扩展到函数外部
if that list is created and returned by that function.
此时列表由函数创建并经函数返回而出
With our examples, the code will be on the left and what's
每个例子都会在左边演示代码
happening within the memory of your computer is visible on the right.
在右边演示计算机内存运行的情况
In this example, we'll see the list is created outside
在本例中 列表在函数外部得到创建
the function and then passed as an argument within the function.
随后会作为参数输入到函数之中
In line one, our list is created in memory with
观察第一行 列表在内存中得到创建
the pointer dogs that points the place in memory where the list is stored.
此时 指针 dogs 指向列表在内存中的存储位置
In line two, we pass the pointer dogs as an argument into the function, edit pets.
第二行 我们将指针 dogs 作为参数输入到函数 edit_pets 中
This creates a second pointer pets that also
从而创建出第二个指针 pets
points to the place in memory where the list is stored.
该指针也指向列表在内存中的存储位置
The pointer pets only exists within the function, edit pets.
指针 pets 只存在于函数 edit_pets 之中
In the first line of edit pets,
函数 edit_pets 的第一行
the value of Cody is popped from the list with the pets pointer.
指针 pets 将列表值 Cody 从列表中弹出
So, the string Cody is removed from the list,
因此 字符串 Cody 被移出了列表
and the rest of the list is adjusted to fill the space vacated by Cody.
列表剩下的内容则会自动调整以填补 Cody 的空缺
With the second line in edit pets,
函数 edit_pets 的第二行
the pointer pets is used to append Bella to the end of the list.
指针 pets 在列表末端追加了 Bella
With the third line in edit pets,
函数 edit_pets 的第三行
the pointer pets is used to append Buddy to the end of the list.
指针 pets 在列表末端追加了 Buddy
Notice that the plus equals operator can be used to append values to the end of a list.
注意 “+=” 运算符的作用就是在列表末端追加值
With the third line in the code,
代码第三行
we print the list dogs.
会输出列表 dogs
Notice that outside of the function,
注意 在函数外部
the pointer pets no longer exists in memory,
内存里已经没有指针 pets 了
but the changes pets made within the function do exist outside of the function.
但 pets 在函数中造成的变化会延续到函数外部
Using the pointer dogs,
使用指针 dogs
the list that will be printed is the one that was
输出的列表
altered by the pointer pets within the function.
会保留指针 pets 在函数内的修改痕迹
In this example, we'll see that a list created inside a function that's not
在本例中 列表会在函数内部得到创建
returned by that function only exists within that function.
但不由函数返回 而且只存在于函数内部
In line one, the function edit pets two is called and nothing exists yet in memory.
第一行调用了函数 edit_pets2 内存还什么都没有
In the first line of edit pets two,
函数 edit_pets2 的第一行
our list is created in memory with the pointer pets
列表在内存中得到创建
that points the place in memory where the list is stored.
其中 指针 pets 指向列表在内存中的存储位置
In the second line of edit pets two,
函数 edit_pets2 的第二行
the value Cody is popped from the list with the pets pointer.
指针 pets 将列表值 Cody 弹出列表
So, the string Cody is removed from the list
因此字符串 Cody 被移出了列表
and the rest of the list is adjusted to fill the space vacated by Cody.
列表剩下的内容则会自动调整以填补 Cody 的空缺
With the third line in edit pets two,
函数 edit_pets2 的第三行
the pointer pets is used to append Bella to the end of the list.
指针 pets 在列表末端追加了 Bella
With the fourth line in edit pets two,
函数 edit_pets2 的第四行
the pointer pets is used to append Buddy to the end of the list.
指针 pets 在列表末端追加了 Buddy
With line two in the code,
代码第二行
we print the string done.
输出字符串 Done 表示已完成操作
Notice that outside of the function,
注意 在函数外部
the pointer pets and the list no longer exist in memory.
指针 pets 和列表不再存在于内存中
In this example, we see that a list created inside a function that is
本例中 列表会在函数内部得到创建
returned by that function exist outside that function.
并经函数返回而出 列表将存在于函数外部
In line one, the function edit pets three is called and nothing exists in memory yet.
第一行调用了函数 edit_pets3 内存还什么都没有
In the first line of edit pets three,
函数 edit_pets3 的第一行
our list is created in memory with
列表在内存中得到创建
the pointer pets that points the place in memory where the list is stored.
其中 指针 pets 指向列表在内存中的存储位置
In the second line of edit pets three,
函数 edit_pets3 的第二行
the value Cody is popped from the list with
指针 pets 将列表值 Cody 弹出了列表
the pets pointer so the string Cody is removed
因此字符串 Cody 被移出了列表
from the list and the rest of the list is adjusted to fill the space vacated by Cody.
列表剩下的内容则会自动调整以填补 Cody 的空缺
With the third line in edit pets three,
函数 edit_pets3 的第三行
the pointer pets is used to append Bella to the end of the list.
指针 pets 在列表末端追加了 Bella
With the fourth line of edit pets three,
函数 edit_pets3 的第四行
the pointer pets is used to append Buddy to the end of the list.
指针 pets 在列表末端追加了 Buddy
With the fifth line and edit pets three the pointer pets is returned from the function.
函数 edit_pets3 的第五行 函数返回出了指针 pets
This creates the pointer dogs that also
由此 程序创建了指针 dogs
points to the place in memory where the list is stored.
该指针也指向列表在内存中的存储位置
Notice that outside of the function,
注意 在函数外部
the pointer pets no longer exists but
内存不再有指针 pets
the pointer dogs and the list still exist in memory,
但仍有指针 dogs 和列表
because the list was returned from the function.
因为函数已经把列表返回出来了
In line two using the pointer dogs,
代码第二行 使用指针 dogs
the list that was created at edit pets three is printed.
输出函数 edit_pets3 创建的列表